Guide to the ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
Throughout the ILGWU’s existence, the greatest concentration of local unions was in New York City, the historic center of the United States garment industry and the city where the International had been founded and maintained its headquarters. This concentration is reflected in the ILGWU Records, as most of the records in this series document the activities of New York City locals.
All told, however, this series contains records of 42 local unions—half of which were based in Boston, Milwaukee, Montreal, Philadelphia, Springfield, and Worcester. Constituted of 63 collections, this series is arranged alphabetically by city, and within city, by local union number.
The density of documentation of local union activity varies considerably, but the types of records are consistent throughout. Again, the records of local unions of New York City are the most extensive, and of these, the records of Local 10, Local 22, Local 62, and Local 89. This is due primarily to the existence of managers’ or other officers’ correspondence, and in the case of Local 22, records of its Education Department. These records reflect not only the routine work of staff and officers of locals, but in several instances, they document the ways that members interacted with their union. In some instances, these were somewhat public affairs relating to disputes and grievances about elections, but in others, they document the ways that members made use of services provided by the local or the International. Also, the more substantive of the collections of local union records illustrate the relationships between members, officers, and staff of a local and state and national politics; see, for example, Isidore Nagler’s correspondence about presidential campaigns or the Liberal Party.
For records of local unions that do not include papers of their staff or officers, the bulk of the documentation takes the form of meeting minutes and publications. Collections of minutes include minutes of meetings of local unions’ membership, and executive board and other committees; collections of publications, in general, contain local unions’ official organ. Some local unions’ records include photographs and audio-visual material which documenting their activities including strikes and rallies, recreational trips, educational classes, conferences, and meetings.
Materials in other series of the ILGWU Records complement the collections organized into this series. The report and record of proceedings in Series I, Constitutions, By-Laws, and Conventions often include some information on the activities of joint boards, district councils, or regional departments of which a local union was a part, if not a report from the local union itself. The records contained in Series IV contain the papers of ILGWU presidents, other officers, and staff; in many cases, these individuals maintained files on local unions or their managers. Likewise, the records of departments and institutions, contained in Series VII, sometimes include either subject or correspondence files on local unions. Series VIII, Printed Material, includes a wide range of publications, including local unions’ newspapers and newsletters; even in cases where the bulk of a local’s publications are contained in Series III, researchers should consult the collections of Series VIII if there are gaps in runs of issues. If not contained in a local union’s own records, it may be possible to locate that affiliate’s collective bargaining agreements in Series VI, Contracts and Files.
Perhaps the most promising of the other series is Series II, Joint Boards, District Councils and Regional Departments. In that series, local unions from the following states are represented: Alabama, Arizona, California, Connecticut, Georgia, Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan, New York, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Utah, Virginia, Washington, West Virginia, Wisconsin. The United States commonwealth of Puerto Rico and the Canadian province of Quebec are also represented in Series II.
The records of ILGWU local unions held at the Kheel Center are the largest concentration of such documentation in the United States, but as even a cursory consideration of the composition of the ILGWU or a quick review of its membership numbers between 1900 and 1995 will indicate, records of a great number of local unions are not held. Researchers should review holdings at other archival repositories, including those listed at the beginning of this finding aid, for records of other local unions of the ILGWU.
SERIES IV. EXECUTIVE OFFICERS AND STAFF, 1911-2006
Series IV, Executive Officers and Staff, consists of 47 collections that document the work of 24 staff and offices of the ILGWU. The collections in this series contain papers, photographs, memorabilia, and audio-visual materials, and they are divided into two subseries: Presidents, and Other Officers and Staff.
Subseries A, Presidents, 1914-1995
Subseries A, Presidents, documents the tenure of 6 ILGWU Presidents: Benjamin Schlesinger (1914-1923, 1928-1932), Morris Sigman (1923-1928), David Dubinsky (1932-1966), Louis Stulberg (1966-1975), Sol Chaikin (1975-1986), and Jay Mazur (1986-1995). The 16 collections constituting this subseries are arranged chronologically by presidential term of service.
The papers of all of the presidents attend to workplace issues and the approaches taken by the ILGWU to address those issues. At the same time, each of the collections of presidential papers highlights issues particular to that moment in the history of the union. For example, Benjamin Schlesinger’s presidential papers are the earliest such documents in the ILGWU Records, and thus provide a unique perspective on the union’s growth and interaction with other organizations in its early years, documenting not only major strikes during his tenure, but other early union activities.
Morris Sigman’s papers document the controversy around communist activity within the union, and the leadership’s efforts to stem the growth of such activity by ILGWU members. These include a series on the 1926 cloakmakers strike in New York City, including union statements, correspondence and memoranda, and financial records.
David Dubinsky’s voluminous papers illustrate the union’s unprecedented growth—whether measured in membership numbers, financial assets, or political power—during his tenure, as well as the international reach that such growth enabled. Dubinsky’s papers include an extensive series of correspondence and subject files, which document the broad interests and investments of Dubinsky and the ILGWU. Dubinsky’s speeches and statements provide an account of the union’s official position on current events, political issues and organizations, as well as a sense of Dubinksy’s rhetorical style. An index to these speeches and statements (Box 399, folder 1) is available.
Because David Dubinsky was deeply involved in very many facets of the union’s operation for over 30 years, his papers should be consulted when considering any aspect of the ILGWU’s work between 1932 and 1966. For example, Dubinsky’s correspondence documents the important roles he played in national and international politics, e.g., his work with the Jewish Labor Committee, the American Labor Party, and the Liberal Party. His collection also provides information about administrative issues within the main office, or matters relating to local unions’ governance. In short, Dubinsky’s “hands-on” leadership on the ILGWU makes his papers a potentially useful resource for any number of research topics.
The papers of subsequent presidents—Stulberg, Chaikin, and Mazur—document not only the work of these individuals, but also the efforts to stem the decline of the union and the garment manufacturing industry in the United States. Louis Stulberg’s papers also address the issues of civil rights and international labor activities, and the union’s shifting alliances with domestic political parties. The papers of Sol Chaikin document the ILGWU’s approaches to dealing with an increase in importation of garments to the United States. Jay Mazur’s papers show the work of the ILGWU to increase membership through new organizing efforts, collaboration within the industry, and expansion of immigration services to members and their families.
Audio recordings (5780 OH) and transcripts (5780/110 OHT) of oral history interviews with David Dubinsky and Louis Stulberg are available.
The presidential records of Herman Grossman (1900-1903, 1905-1907), James McCauley (1904-1905), Mortimer Julian and Charles Jacobson (1907-1908), and Abraham Rosenberg (1908-1914), as well as the records of Benjamin Schlesinger’s first tenure as ILGWU president (1903-1904) are not held at the Kheel Center. Their location is unknown.
Subseries B, Other Officers and Staff, 1911-2006
Subseries B, Other Officers and Staff, includes the records of Myrtle Banks, Martin Berger, Muzaffar Chishti, Susan Cowell, Wilbur Daniels, Joseph Good, Murray Gross, Alan Howard, James Lipsig, Jay Mazur, David Melman, James Parrott, Carl Proper, Irwin Solomon, Leon Stein, Gus Tyler, and Frederick Umhey. Also included are the records of Louis Stulberg’s tenure as General Secretary-Treasurer, and the Office Employees International Union (OEIU) local 153. The 31 collections comprising this subseries are arranged in alphabetical order by surname.
The collections in this subseries originated from a variety of offices within the ILGWU’s international headquarters. The finding aids to these collections offer details about these different origins, but several characteristics about the materials are consistent throughout.
One, ILGWU staff and officers were often involved in several projects at once, and the papers in this subseries reflect this concurrent work. For example, James Lipsig’s papers document both his work as Assistant Executive Secretary and, from 1966 to 1976, as Treasurer of the ILGWU Campaign Committee, and other materials relating to Lipsig’s work might be found in the Political Department records of Evelyn Dubrow from that period (5780/119). Likewise, Leon Stein’s papers include material for his book The Triangle Fire, but they also contain documents relating to his book on the 1914 Ludlow (Colorado) massacre.
Two, in addition to being involved in concurrent projects, many staff and officers held different positions in sequence, thus the materials in this subseries provide an incomplete picture of staff members’ work over time. Jay Mazur, for example, had a long career in the ILGWU, and a researcher interested a comprehensive study of his work will find only a segment of it in this subseries. Review of Local 40’s records, Local 23-25’s records, and Mazur’s presidential papers would complement the papers in this series (5780/154) from his tenure as Secretary-Treasurer. The same holds true for the work of Louis Stulberg, who worked in Local 81 (Chicago) and Local 10 before serving in executive positions and finally, being elected president of the ILGWU.
Finally and along the same lines, all of the collections in this subseries are complemented by collections in other series of the ILGWU Records. The files on the Garment Industry Development Corporation (GIDC) in James Parrott’s paper and the Council on American Fashion (CAF) in Muzaffar Chishti’s papers complement one another, as well as the records of the Apparel Job Training and Research Corporation (5780/114), insofar as they all document cooperative efforts between the ILGWU, local and national government, and industry to buoy the women’s garment manufacturing industry in the United States. Gus Tyler’s papers, especially those that contain his columns and transcripts from his radio broadcasts (5780/096) obviously complement Leon Stein’s collection of writings, but they also pair well with the speeches, reports, and grey literature of the Education Department (578/166 PUBS).
Collections of audio recordings (5780 OH) and transcripts (5780/110 OHT) of oral history interviews of 45 officers, staff, and members of the ILGWU are also available.
SERIES V. GENERAL EXECUTIVE BOARD, 1900-1995
The General Executive Board (GEB) was the highest governing authority of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union, except when the ILGWU constitution stated otherwise. The GEB’s responsibilities included participation in the negotiation of collective bargaining agreements; authorization of strikes and the use of funds in relation to such actions; supervision of the subordinate affiliates of the ILGWU, i.e., regional departments, district councils, joint boards and councils, and local unions; supervision of departments and institutions within the International office; and oversight of financial and administrative matters.
In addition to these duties, the GEB was responsible for the appointment of an executive committee from its own ranks, as well as the appointment or election of individuals to standing and special committees. Though “standing,” standing committees came into and out of being over the course of the ILGWU’s existence. In 1950, for example, the GEB appointed seven standing committees: Finance Committee, Grievance and Appeal Committee, Educational Committee, Death Benefit Committee, Jurisdiction Committee, Health and Welfare Funds Committee, and Press Committee. By 1965 (and through 1992), the standing committees were reduced to five: Appeals, Education and Community Relations, Finance, Workers’ Benefits, and Jurisdiction.
As for the composition of the GEB itself, while the individuals serving on the GEB changed with elections at the ILGWU’s regular conventions, as well as through retirement or departure from the garment industry, the general composition of the board remained for the most part consistent throughout the ILGWU’s existence. The GEB was composed of the President, General Secretary-Treasurer, and a number of vice-presidents and executive vice-presidents; the number, title, and responsibilities of those vice-presidents changed over time. Meetings were held at least semi-annually, though in some years the GEB met more frequently.
This series consists of meeting minutes, reports, correspondence, and other materials of the General Executive Board of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers Union. Included are resolutions of the GEB and ILGWU affiliates, GEB election results, and in many instances, indexes to GEB minutes. Also included are reports from the ILGWU’s departments and affiliates, and reports from the GEB’s standing committees, special committees, and executive committee. The work of the GEB’s Appeal Committee, Election and Objection Committee, and Grievance Committee are especially well-documented; those committees’ case files include correspondence between the International office and ILGWU affiliates relating to members’ cases, notes on cases, notices of decisions, evidence presented to the committee in appeals, and meeting minutes.
Because the General Executive Board had supervisory authority over all ILGWU departments and affiliates and, in turn, those departments and affiliates provided regular and formal reports to the General Executive Board, the collections in this series are among the most complete in the ILGWU records. The regular reports from ILGWU affiliates highlight their work and complement, or perhaps contradict, the records elsewhere in the ILGWU Records that document their work in greater details. In some instances, reports to the GEB are the full extent of the non-published documentation of an affiliates work. Thus, the reports to the General Executive Board begin to fill out gaps in other parts of the records.
Of course, in addition to recording the work of the many entities that reported to the GEB, the records of the GEB also reflect the priorities and strategies of the ILGWU leadership. This documentation is most evident in the meeting minutes of the GEB’s executive committee. Researchers interested in this aspect of the ILGWU should also consult the papers of the members of the GEB. In many instances, the papers of the union’s presidents and other officers include files on the GEB. In some instances, these files duplicate the records of this series, but in other instances, they complement the minutes of and reports to the GEB, including correspondence and other related material. Likewise, where gaps exist, researchers should also review the papers of executive assistants; they, too, maintained files on the GEB and several of its committees.
SERIES VI. CONTRACTS AND CASE FILES, 1907-2000
Series VI, Contracts and Case Files, is comprised of 7 collections of collective bargaining agreements (CBAs) negotiated by the ILGWU.
At the core of this series is a general collection of CBAs (5780/075 and 5780/075mf) that were in effect between 1907 and 2000. These include agreements with independent companies and associations of manufacturers, negotiated by individual local unions, joint boards, and after its establishment in 1965, the Master Agreements Department. These two collections are supplemented by a third (5780/191), which consists of CBAs negotiated with associations of manufacturers and effective between 1916 and 1994.
The remaining collections in this series are comprised of contracts that the ILGWU filed as “Out of Business,” meaning that the contract was with an independent manufacturer that had gone out of business or with an association of manufacturers that had dissolved. These include contracts negotiated by the Master Agreements Department (5780/146), and by local unions, joint boards, and joint councils (5780/147 and 5780/158) with individual companies. One collection (5780/145) contains contracts with out-of-business associations of manufacturers.
While this series contains the bulk of collective bargaining agreements within the ILGWU Records, additional CBAs may be found throughout the collection. The records of Local 62-32 (5780/089), for example, primarily consists of that union’s agreements. Other local unions, joint boards and councils, district councils, and regional departments may contain agreements pertaining to their own or others’ areas. The papers of presidents, officers, and other staff may also contain agreements, as well as notes and correspondence relating to their negotiation. The papers of Wilbur Daniels (5780/113), for example, contain documents from during his tenure as Director of the Master Agreements Department. Likewise, the papers of Jay Mazur (5780/203) contains notes, memoranda, and news clippings about contract negotiations while he was president of the ILGWU.
In addition to CBAs in this series and dispersed throughout the rest of the ILGWU Records, researchers will find additional ILGWU agreements in other collections at the Kheel Center. These include the Archival Collective Bargaining Agreements File (6030) and the collection of collective bargaining agreements from the United States Department of Labor’s Bureau of Labor Statistics (6178).
SERIES VII. DEPARTMENTS AND INSTITUTIONS, 1884-1999
The ILGWU’s international office maintained departments and institutions to organize and advance the union’s work. This series consists of 56 collections documenting the work of 20 of these departments and institutions, arranged alphabetically by name. Taken together, they document the national and often international reach of the ILGWU’s work.
The scope and content of the collections varies, thus the daily operations and special projects of some departments are more fully documented than others. The Research Department’s records, for example, not only include everyday administrative records and department reports on the garment industry, but also some of the sources that research department staff consulted in the course of their work. By contrast, the records of the Communications Department consist entirely of subject and biographical files that while providing helpful biographical information on ILGWU staff and officers, do not clearly indicate how the organization routinely operated. Likewise, the collection for the ILGWU Library is in its entirety a photocopy of the catalog cards.
In some instances, the records of a department are divided further into collections of files maintained by individuals. The records of the Education Department exemplify this. For that department, there are collections created by four former staff members and one central file, all named accordingly. Together, they comprise the department’s records.
In other instances, certain individuals were long-time or founding directors of a department; their names were synonymous with the department for a period; and their files constitute the bulk of the written documentation on the department. The Retiree Services Department and the David Dubinsky Foundation, both organized around the time of David Dubinsky’s retirement in 1966, are examples of this. Likewise, the bulk of the Political Department Records at the Kheel Center were maintained by Evelyn Dubrow. In these cases, the names of the directors appear in the title of the collection.
In yet other instances, the records of a department are neither concentrated in the records maintained by a single director nor divided into files of several individual staff members. The records of the Apparel Job Training and Research Corporation, for example, primarily consist of application forms, and it is not apparent who collected, organized, and maintained them. The same is true of the relatively small collection of Union Health Center records, as well as a collection of publications from the Auditing Department.
For the most part, whether associated with a prominent ILGWU figure or not, the collections in this series contain sufficient records to assist in ascertaining the primary function of a department or institution, and to complement the published accounts of their work in the ILGWU’s official organ Justice or the union's Report and Record of Proceedings.
Beyond this, several elements of this series may be of interest to researchers. More than any of the other segments of the ILGWU Records, the records of the Archives Department and the Research Department cover a broad chronological scope. The records of the Archives Department contain a copy of the founding minutes of the ILGWU (5780/111, box 1, folder 13), as well as notes and interviews with union leaders. The oral histories conducted by the ILGWU Archives Department (5780 OH and 5780/110 OHT) constitute the bulk of such interviews with ILGWU officials at the Kheel Center. Early documents held in the Research Department Records include meeting minutes of the ILGWU predecessor union Sanctuary Local Assembly 3038 of the Knights of Labor.
The aforementioned biographical files of the Communications Department are of interest not only because they provide sometimes difficult-to-find, basic information on ILGWU members and officers, but because that information was provided by the individuals themselves, on forms provided by the union and designed to be returned to the office when completed. Organizational self-reporting is documented in the small collection of publications from the Auditing Department. These annual reports of membership, affiliates, and income provide information on the steady growth, and later, decline in the union’s number of local unions and members, as well as clear reportage of the breakdown of the organization by city, region, and territory.